<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>js on Tech grumbling</title><link>https://cardinalby.github.io/blog/tags/js/</link><description>Recent content in js on Tech grumbling</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>cardinalby</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cardinalby.github.io/blog/tags/js/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>JavaScript GitHub Action packing and releasing</title><link>https://cardinalby.github.io/blog/post/github-actions/js-action-packing-and-releasing/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cardinalby.github.io/blog/post/github-actions/js-action-packing-and-releasing/</guid><description>🔭 Overview In this article I want to share some undocumented details of creating JavaScript GitHub Actions related to the using of ncc packing tool.
It&amp;rsquo;s not just a step-by-step instruction, but the story describing the problem, the proposed approach and the reasoning behind it.
If you are just looking for a quick code example, jump to this one and come back for an explanation 🙂
🎬 Basics that you already know The basic approach is pretty easy and described in GitHub documentation here.</description></item><item><title>GitHub Actions integration testing lib</title><link>https://cardinalby.github.io/blog/project/github-actions-testing-lib/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cardinalby.github.io/blog/project/github-actions-testing-lib/</guid><description>Check out https://github.com/cardinalby/github-action-ts-run-api
Purpose 🔶 Executing your GitHub action locally (or at any other environment).
🔶 Writing integration and functional tests, run them locally and at CI.
🔶 Having a short feedback loop without pushing and checking it behaviour at real GitHub runners every time.
Features ✅ Supports executing JavaScript and Docker actions.
✅ Tested under Windows, Linux and macOS locally and on GitHub hosted runners.
✅ Works well with Docker Desktop under Windows and macOS (for Docker actions).</description></item><item><title>Testing of JavaScript Actions</title><link>https://cardinalby.github.io/blog/post/github-actions/testing/2-testing-of-js-actions/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cardinalby.github.io/blog/post/github-actions/testing/2-testing-of-js-actions/</guid><description>Let&amp;rsquo;s talk about JavaScript GitHub Actions and approaches that we can apply on the different levels of testing.
Unit tests From my point of view, unit testing of Actions doesn&amp;rsquo;t have any differences from testing any other JavaScript code. In most of the examples of Actions available on the GitHub Marketplace authors don&amp;rsquo;t care about writing testable code. But nothing prevents you from extracting abstractions and following The Dependency Inversion Principle which will allow you to easily mock dependencies (such as @actions/core , @actions/github, @actions/exec packages).</description></item><item><title>Memrise Audio Uploader</title><link>https://cardinalby.github.io/blog/project/memrise-audio-uploader/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cardinalby.github.io/blog/project/memrise-audio-uploader/</guid><description>Memrise Audio Uploader is a Chrome extension which allows you to upload sounds of words and phrases pronunciation from soundoftext.com to memrise.com course.
Check out the source code https://github.com/cardinalby/memrise-audio-uploader
Install from the stores Chrome Web Store
Firefox Add-ons
To download the offline versions please go to the Releases page.
Screenshots</description></item></channel></rss>